Raphael Amiard

Senior compiler and language frontend engineer

- E-mail:raph.amiard@gmail.com
- Website:raph-amiard.github.io

I am a language geek. My passion is in compilers and language design. I developed several interpreters, worked on a few compilers, and designed or helped design several computer languages.

I'm fluent in many computer languages, and can learn new ones easily.

Work experience

2013-2023 - AdaCore

Compiler/language front-end engineer. Lead developper/team manager

- Lead developper/manager of the Libadalang & Langkit projects.
 - Ada front-end which powers a big portion of the Ada tools at AdaCore, including our IDEs, code style
 checkers, and static analysis tools
 - I originally started the projects on my own, closely followed by a colleague
 - 10 years later I manage a 5 developper team driving the development/maintenance/R&D around those projects.
 - Presentation about Langkit at FOSDEM 2018: Langkit: source code analyzers for the masses
 - Presentation about Libadalang at FOSDEM 2018: Easy Ada Tooling with Libadalang
- Lead developer & manager of LKQL, a query language for syntax trees.
 - Powers the GNATcheck style checker
 - Allows the quick & easy definition of checkers from syntax patterns
- Member of the Ada Rapporteur Group (group in charge of the standardization of the Ada language) since 2015.
- Lead language design at AdaCore.
 - Role: Leading & coordinating the working groups around language evolutions.
 - Led working group on pattern matching
 - Leading working group on improved generics
- Initial developper (together with @derodat) of the GNAT-llvm project, a middle-end for the GNAT compiler to emit LLVM IR.
- Co-authored and presented Application of SMT in a Meta-Compiler: A Logic DSL for Specifying Type Systems, together with Romain Beguet.
- Co-wrote the Introduction to Ada course/book.

2016-2023 - EPITA

- Teacher at EPITA for the **GISTRE** (Génie Informatique des systèmes temps réel et embarqués) major.
- Teaching Ada, realtime/embedded programming, and Rust since 2020.

2012 - Google Summer of Code:

- Modularisation of the ClojureScript compiler's backend (Clojure to Javascript compiler).
- Development of a new Lua backend.

2010-2011 - Freelance web developper:

- Freelance for e-loue Python Django development. Development of a dynamic application backed by a rest API, using Django/Tastypie and backbone.js.
- Four months internship at **Paperblog** news and information website, using Python Django Infrastructure and front-end development. Web scraping engine using Coffeescript.

Education

- 2010-2012 Master « Distributed systems and applications » Pierre et Marie Curie (Paris VI) university
- 2008-2010 Licence in Computer Science first class Pierre et Marie Curie (Paris VI) university
- 2003-2008 Master in Human Sciences, Sociology major René Descartes (Paris V) university

Others

Personal projects

- Camllym An LLVM based bytecode compiler for OCaml.
- ada-synth-lib A very simple sound/music synthesis library.
- lune A small functional language with Hindley-Milner type inference and typeclasses

Personal interests

- Electronic music creator and lover. Released several projects in digital or vinyl over the years.
- Co-created the https://excellentchoix.bandcamp.com/ music label